Guide to the Larry Racioppo collection BCMS.0053
Center for Brooklyn History
Larry Racioppo collection
1971-2024
Center for Brooklyn History
Racioppo, Larry
BCMS.0053
8.8 Linear Feet in 5 flat boxes, 4 document boxes, 2 cartons, 2 legal size boxes
Materials documenting the career of New York based photographer Larry Racioppo.
Related Materials
Oral history interview conducted with Larry Racioppo on April 5, 2018.
Racioppo, Larry. Brooklyn before: photographs, 1971-1983. Three Hills, an imprint of Cornell University Press. 2018. 779.99747 R
Racioppo, Larry. Halloween. Scribner. 1980. 779.9394 R
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Series 1: Exhibits is arranged chronologically. When multiple exhibits appear in a given year the folders are arranged alphabetically by exhibit space.
Series 2: Press is arranged chronologically.
Series 3: Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject with the exception of the Department of Housing Preservation and Development, which is foldered together regardless of subject.
Series 4: Freelance Assignments is arranged alphabetically by the hiring organization.
Series 5: New York City Department of Housing Preservation and Development is arranged alphabetically by project.
Series 6: Project Notes and Research is arranged alphabetically by project.
Series 7: Photographs is boxed by print size.
Provenance
This collection was acquired between 2014-2025 through a series of purchases and donations from Larry Racioppo.
Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of items documenting the career of New York based photographer Larry Racioppo. Exhibit materials for both solo and group shows span over 40 years and include promotional materials, photographs and notes. Correspondence includes communications regarding funding opportunities, his Guggenheim Fellowship, recommendations and thank you notes from professional contacts.
Reports, brochures and calendars make up the bulk of Racioppo's freelance assignments and his work for the Department of Housing Preservation and Development. Research materials for personal photography projects include scouting and shooting notes with copies of relevant maps and atlas pages. The Theater Project makes up the bulk of the Project Notes and Research series.
Photographs printed for various exhibits and publications are also included. Folders that include publications are dated to reflect the year of publication, not the date of the included photographs.
Biographical Note
Larry Racioppo was born and raised in South Brooklyn, and has been photographing throughout New York City since 1971. A former VISTA Volunteer, and participant in NYC's Cultural Council Foundation's CETA Artists Project, Racioppo had his first solo exhibit in 1977 at Brooklyn's f-stop Gallery. His first book of photographs, Halloween, was published by Scribners in 1980.
From 1989-2011, Larry was the official photographer for NYC's Department of Housing Preservation and Development, hired to document the city's rebuilding of distressed neighborhoods, including Bedford Stuyvesant, Harlem and the South Bronx. After receiving a Guggenheim Fellowship in Photography in 1997, Racioppo took a leave from HPD to work on a series of personal projects, including FORGOTTEN GATEWAY, the Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, a travelling exhibit of his photographs that originated at the National Building Museum in Washington, D.C.
In 2006 he was awarded a National Endowment for the Arts Chairman's Extraordinary Action Grant for his exhibit The Word on the Street at the Museum of Biblical Art in New York. Racioppo's photographs are in the collections of the Museum of the City of New York, The Brooklyn Museum, the New York Public Library, El Museo del Barrio, and the National September 11 Memorial & Museum. His second book, Brooklyn Before: Photographs, 1971–1983 was published by Cornell University Press in 2018.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
A portion of the materials in this collection are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org at least three weeks prior to research visit.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Photographs; Photography -- Exhibitions; Street photography
- Series 1: Exhibits
  - Early Exhibits, 1974-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Eleventh Street Photo Gallery. Halloween, 1979 (Folder Flat File)
  - Museum of African American History and Arts. Rebuilding Harlem, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2, Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bronx Museum, Satellite Gallery. Rebuilding the Bronx, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Midtown Y Photography Gallery. The Mermaid Parade, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4, Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Alexander Hamilton U.S. Custom House. Civic Lessons, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alliance of Queens Artists. Full Spectrum/Image and Imagination III, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Art Center of Northern New Jersey. Steel Water Light, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jamaica Arts Center. The Outskirts of Town, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Municipal Arts Society. Reasons for Hope, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pace University. Coney Island Photographs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Print Club. Primary Subject, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Times Square Lobby Gallery. Almost Home, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Center for Art and Culture of Bedford-Stuyvesant, Inc. Theosophy-N-Art, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brooklyn Borough Hall. Home Ownership in Brooklyn, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Times Square Lobby Gallery. The Nature of Our Environment, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Hudson River Museum. Getting From Here to There, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Museum of the City of New York. New York Begins, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Republic National Bank of New York. Community Renaissance, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Building Museum. Forgotten Gateway: The Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 19, Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Museum of the City of New York. Landscapes of Hope, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - New York Public Library. Disorder Order, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Westchester Gallery. New York, the Lost City, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gallery Five. Worship, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Museum of the City of New York. Forgotten Gateway: The Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Museum of the City of New York. New York Now 2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Godwin-Ternbach Museum (CUNY). A Vision of the Street, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Henry Street Settlement. Sacred Spaces: Lower East Side Shuls +1, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - New Jersey State Museum. Forgotten Gateway: The Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Deutsche Bank. The Mural as Muse, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Municipal Society. Fresh Kills: The Photographs, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - New Jersey Historical Society. Forgotten Gateway: The Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The River Edge Cultural Center. From Ellis Island to the Golden Land, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Rotunda Gallery. To Market to Market, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Save Ellis Island. Forgotten Gateway: The Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - St. Paul's Chapel. Out of the Dust, circa 2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ellis Island Immigration Museum. Forgotten Gateway: The Abandoned Buildings of Ellis Island, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Box 36)
  - Brooklyn Public Library. All This Useless Beauty, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Brooklyn Public Library. World Religions of Brooklyn, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Safe-T-Gallery. O Giglio E Paradiso, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 39, Folder Flat File)
  - Enterprise Reception Winter Garden. HPD Photography, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Interfaith Center of New York. Frames of Reverence, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Municipal Arts Society. Keeping the Faith, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - La Guardia Community College. Going to Look for America, circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Center for Photography at Woodstock. Relationships: A Ten Year Bond, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Museum of Biblical Art. The Word on the Street, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 45, Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Museum of the City of New York. New York Comes Back: Mayor Ed Koch and the City, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - The Goodwin-Ternbach Museum. A Vision of the Street, 2006 (Folder Flat File)
  - Museum of the City of New York. Catholics in New York 1808-1946, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Safe-T-Gallery. Brooklyn Interiors, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Yeh Art Gallery. Influences of African Beliefs on Latin American Contemporary Alters: An Exhibition of Alters and Ritual Offerings, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Garibaldi-Meucci Museum. Kitty and Lucky: Photographs of My Aunt Concetta and Uncle Augustine, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 50, Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Art + Cayce. Larry Racioppo Photographer, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - BRIC. 30, a Brooklyn Salon, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - New York City Health and Hospital Corporation. NYC in Focus, Volume 2, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - El Museo Del Barrio. Voces Y Visiones: Gran Caribe, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Brooklyn Arts Council. Sea Drift, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Valentine Museum of Art. Coney Island, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Brooklyn College. From Brooklyn College to Coney Island, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Brooklyn Public Library. Looking Out/Looking In, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Series 2: Press
  - The Journal of the Theater Historical Society, circa 1980-2005 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Neighborhood, 1983 (Summer) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bricks + Mortar, 1993 (Fall) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Community News, 1992 (Nov.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Bridge Magazine, 1998 (June, Oct., Dec.) (Box 2, Folder 3, Folder Flat File)
  - Common Bond, 1999 (Spring/Summer) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Culture Front Magazine, 1999 (Summer, Fall) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Queens Life, 2000 (April) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 2000-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Metro, 2007 (Sept.) (Folder Flat File)
  - ArtNews, 2013 (April) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Correspondence
  - Department of Housing Preservation and Development, 2004-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Guggenheim, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters of Acceptance and Recommendation, 1997-2001, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rejections, 1994-2014 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Thank You Letters, 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series 4: Freelance Assignments
  - Brooklyn Historical Society, Red Hook Guide, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society, Williamsburg Guide, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chase Manhattan, Corporate Responsibility Annual Report, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Take the Field, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - International Longshoremen's Association, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19, Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Queens Council on the Arts, Annual Reports, 2000, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Yale University, Wolf Head's Society, circa 2005 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 5: New York City Department of Housing Preservation and Development
  - Condition Reports, circa 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - HPD Pipeline Newsletter, 1995 (Jan.) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Housing Development Corporation, Annual Reports, 1998-2008 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Landmarks Conservancy, Annual Reports, 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The New Housing Marketplace, Progress Reports, 2003, 2005, 2008, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Supportive Housing Network, circa 2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Reports, circa 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Neighborhood Entrepreneurs Program, circa 2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - New York City Home, circa 1998 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Deck of Cards (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Housing, New York City Cover Proof, 1999 (Folder Flat File)
  - Single Room Living in New York City Cover Proof (Folder Flat File)
- Series 6: Project Notes and Research
  - Brooklyn Before, 2017-2018 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Brooklyn Book of the Dead (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Giglio, circa 1995-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3, Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Halloween, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4, Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Theaters, Brooklyn Drawings (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Theaters, Clippings, 1975-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Theaters, Drawings (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Theaters, Found (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Theaters, Gone (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Theaters, Location and Access with Maps (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Theaters, Locations and Contacts (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Theaters, Locations not Photographed (Box 3, Folder 12, Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Theaters, Loew's Kings Proposal (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Theaters, Photographed (Box 3, Folder 14, Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Theaters, Photographed but Incomplete (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Theaters, Polaroids and Contacts with Notes (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Theaters, Shooting Notes (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook (Box 4)
- Series 7: Photographs
  - Calendars, 2000-2001, 2018, 2024 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - BRIC-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - BRIC Calendar (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Churches (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Coney Island Mermaid Parade (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Holy Family School, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Greenpoint Hospital, circa 2007 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Questua, 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Coney Island Mermaid Parade (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Coney Island/Theater, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 3, Folder Flat File)
  - Churches, 1990-2008 (Box 6, Folder 4, Folder Flat File)
  - Giglio (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Landscapes of Hope (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Landscapes of Hope (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lowe's Kings Theater, 1998-2001 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Scrap (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - B-Ball NYC: Proofs (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Books, 2009-2022 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Books, Shutterfly, 2017-2022 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - BRIC 2000 Calendar/HDC (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Coney Island Mermaid Parade (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Giglio, Printed for Show, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Good Friday (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Prospect Park (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Joe and Mary's 50th Anniversary Party, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ray K's Bachelor Party, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 4x5 Work, circa 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Subjects include: Clinton Hill Church, Sisters of Mercy, family, St. John's statues, crosses, 24th Street schoolyard, fig trees on 6th Avenue, and a sidewalk.
  - Word on the Street, 1995-2005 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Larry's Sandy Diary, 2022 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    This book includes images of Hurricane Sandy, captured in 2012.
  - Brooklyn Before, 1971-1983 (Box 11)
  - B-Ball NYC: Correspondence and Notes (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - B-Ball NYC: Outtakes (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - B-Ball NYC: First Set of Proofs (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - B-Ball NYC: Proofs (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - B-Ball NYC: Book and Calendar, Shutterfly (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Clinton Hill Restoration, Paperwork (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Clinton Hill Restoration, Photographs, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - Coney Island Baby, Original Mockup, circa 2020 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Coney Island Baby, Printer's Proofs, 2021 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Coney Island Baby, Coney Island USA Copies, circa 2020 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Coney Island Baby, Correspondence, 2021 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Coney Island Baby, Essays, circa 2021 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Coney Island Baby, Notes and Research, circa 2020-2021 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Bill Grandner's mural of the Brooklyn Bridge, backyard on Frost Street, 2001 (Folder Flat File CBH)